Alright, boker tov בוקר טוב, boker tov, erev Purim tov ערב פורים
טוב, erev Purim tov, I guess better than saying Gut Taanis Esther
tov גוט תענית אסתר טוב. gut taanis esther tov. Alright, so today's
daf דף daf is yud-beis י"ב. yud-beis. Quiet please, gentlemen. Today's daf
דף daf is yud-beis י"ב yud-beis and it's going to continue a
lot with this discussion about coinage, and we are still dealing with
this issue about how do we know according to Beis Shammai בית
שמאי beis shammai that what's the basis to say that a dinar
דינר dinar is the minimum amount that a woman could be married
if a perutah פרוטה perutah is the minimum amount of money. So
we have one explanation which is more sort of a subjective explanation
of ada'ata אדעתא, ada'ata, like a presumption that women would not agree
to less than a dinar דינר, dinar, which the Gemara גמרא gemara
sort of challenged. We have another explanation that since it's based on
kesef כסף kesef in the Torah תורה, torah, kesef כסף kesef in
the Torah תורה torah the minimum amount is kesef Tzuri כסף צורי
kesef tzuri which is silver coinage. The problem being though, part of
the problem being that that would not put you at a dinar
דינר, dinar, it would put you at a ma'ah מעה. ma'ah. And
anyway for other reasons the Gemara גמרא gemara says that when it
says kesef כסף kesef generically it's not a particular coin and it
could even include a perutah פרוטה. perutah. And that the real when
we say that kesef כסף kesef in the Torah תורה torah means
specific, you know, kesef Tzuri
כסף צורי, kesef tzuri, silver coinage and a particular type of silver
coinage, that's only when the Torah תורה torah gives an exact amount:
30, 50, etc. Then you have to really know the denomination. Okay,
so we're back to the question of what's the basis of Beis
Shammai בית שמאי. beis shammai. And now the thing we said is
that basically that the answer was,
anyway why don't we just read it from the top. Reish Lakish
ריש לקיש, reish lakish, so we'll start again from like eight lines
from the bottom of yud-aleph amud beis י"א עמוד ב. yud-aleph amud
beis. Reish Lakish omer ריש לקיש אומר, reish lakish omer, ta'ama d'Vei
Shammai k'd'Chizkiyah טעמא דבי שמאי כדחזקיה. ta'ama d'bei shammai k'd'chizkiyah. The reason
is like Chizkiyah. D'amar Chizkiyah amar kra דאמר חזקיה אמר קרא, d'amar
chizkiyah amar kra, the verse says v'hefdah והפדה v'hefdah by the amah
ivriyah אמה עבריה amah ivriyah sold by the father and we're going
to use the selling of the amah ivriyah אמה עבריה amah ivriyah
by the father as a model for the father marrying the daughter
in kiddushin קידושין, kiddushin, which we've seen before. Melamed she-megara'at mipidyona v'yotza
מלמד שמגרעת מפדיונה ויוצאה. melamed she-megara'at mipidyona v'yotza. The word v'hefdah והפדה
v'hefdah teaches that the slave can redeem herself, or her self in
this case, and that actually that it's you pro-rate the amount that
they have to pay to redeem themselves based on the amount that
they've served so far, the amount of labor that they've done so
far. Okay, so if that's true, so that means that you have
to have the original sale price was something that could be pro-rated,
was more than a penny, alright? Or else there's no opportunity to
pro-rate. Ee amart b'shlama d'yahav lah dinar אי אמרת בשלמא דיהב לה
דינר, ee amart b'shlama d'yahav lah dinar, if you had paid a
dinar דינר dinar for her, which is close to 200 perutahs פרוטות,
perutahs, okay. Haino d'megara'at v'azla ad perutah היינו דמגרעת ואזלא עד פרוטה,
haino d'megara'at v'azla ad perutah, then you could pro-rate there, you know
if she'd served half the time then you would do it whatever,
you'd pay half. Okay, ella ee amart d'yahav lah perutah אלא
אי אמרת דיהב לה פרוטה, ella ee amart d'yahav lah perutah, so
if it was only paid a perutah פרוטה perutah to begin with,
so miprutah mee megara מפרוטה מי מגרע, miprutah mee megara, there's nothing
to detract, there's nothing to pro-rate from that.
So it had to have been a dinar דינר, dinar, right. So
we'll get to that. So first the Gemara גמרא gemara has a
different question. V'dilma hachi ka-amar rachmana ודלמא הכי קאמר רחמנא, v'dilma hachi
ka-amar rachmana, maybe this is what the Torah תורה torah says. Heicha
d'yahav lah dinar tegara ad perutah היכא דיהב לה דינר תגרע עד
פרוטה, heicha d'yahav lah dinar tegara ad perutah, maybe the Torah תורה
torah is saying look, if it's possible to pro-rate, like a dinar
דינר dinar was paid for her to begin with, then you can
pro-rate until there's like a perutah פרוטה perutah left, you can't go
below a perutah פרוטה, perutah, you have to minimally do a perutah
פרוטה perutah to redeem her. Okay, but
heicha d'yahav lah perutah היכא דיהב לה פרוטה, heicha d'yahav lah perutah,
if it was a case only a perutah פרוטה perutah was paid
for her, lo tegara klal לא תגרע כלל, lo tegara klal, maybe
there is no option. Meaning maybe she could still be bought for
a perutah פרוטה perutah and in that case there would be no
pro-rating and when the Torah תורה torah discussed about pro-rating that was
when more than a penny was paid for her. So before the
question about how do you know it's a dinar דינר, dinar, maybe
it's one of these middle coins, the question is: okay, just because
there's an option to pro-rate doesn't mean every case has to have
that scenario. Maybe there's a case that has a perutah פרוטה. perutah.
So the Gemara גמרא gemara says no, lo salka daiteich לא סלקא
דעתך, lo salka daiteich, that doesn't make sense. Dumya d'yiud דומיא דיעוד,
dumya d'yiud, because we'd say the same thing we say about yiud
יעוד. yiud. Remember when an amah ivriyah אמה עבריה amah ivriyah sold,
the goal is for the master to make her his wife, to
be meyayed מייעד meyayed her, for him or for his son. Now
what now, so that's you could say that's an option. What about
a scenario where there would not be an option for yiud יעוד?
yiud? What would be a scenario? Let's say somebody sold his daughter
to his, to his,
I don't know, let's say a crazy example, to his father. Okay,
let's say or to his
son. Somebody's you know, his son was wealthy, he wasn't, he was
hard on whatever. Anyway, so now the man who has bought this
girl as an amah ivriyah אמה עבריה amah ivriyah cannot marry her,
it's an arayos עריות arayos to him. You got the case? Okay.
Or if you want a case that's maybe less crazy, let's say
he sold it to a man who had already married this girl's
sister. He sold his daughter to a man who had married this
girl's sister. Okay. So you say fine, that's a good sale, yiud
יעוד yiud isn't an option in that case. But we don't say
that. We say if yiud יעוד yiud isn't an option, there's no
sale. Okay, ma yiud מה יעוד. ma yiud. you could say ייעוד
Yi'ud is just an option, you don't have to be מייעד, me'ade,
so the, you know, but we would say כל היכא דלא מצי
מייעד kol heicha de-la matzi miyad nevertheless we say כל היכא דלא
מצי מייעד kol heicha de-la matzi miyad if ייעוד Yi'ud doesn't have
to take place but it has to be possible and if ייעוד
Yi'ud is not possible לאו זביני זביני lav zvini zvini it would
not be a good sale. So הכא נמי hacha nami so we'll
say the same here כל היכא דלא מצי מגרע kol heicha de-la
matzi migra if there's not an option to free her by, you
know, paying by reducing the amount לאו זביני זביני lav zvini zvini
would it be good? So every case has to have a case
of the possibility for reducing the amount, okay? So a
פרוטה perutah would never be enough, you'd always have to have a
higher point of sale to give the ability to reduce the amount,
if that ability wasn't there the sale wouldn't be good. And therefore
it's not a פרוטה, perutah, so if it's not a פרוטה perutah
it's got to be a דינר, dinar, and I still don't explain
why not any of those middle coins. And by the way one
should point out there's a big difference between this and between ייעוד.
Yi'ud. ייעוד Yi'ud you could say the point that the Torah the
reason the Torah allowed a father to sell his daughter into slavery
was only because of the hope and anticipation that the guy would
marry her. That not that real I mean you know so that's
what the whole point of the institution was. And if ייעוד Yi'ud
isn't on the table then there's no then then we don't allow
it. Whereas here if he sold her for a פרוטה perutah and
קידושין kiddushin for a פרוטה perutah why would why should we not
allow the sale just because you can't go lower than a פרוטה?
perutah? But okay the גמרא Gemara is saying no there has to
be it has to be a higher point of sale. There has
to be the possibility of reducing the the amount. So גמרא Gemara
says okay וקידושי אשה ve-kiddushei ishah and that's stage number one. So
we know from selling the daughter into slavery it's more than a
פרוטה. perutah. וקידושי אשה לבית שמאי נפקא ליה מאמה עבריה ve-kiddushei ishah
le-Beit Shammai nafka lei me-amah ivriyah and he would learn out the
קידושין kiddushin of a woman from the father's sale of his daughter
as a slave. מה אמה עבריה בפרוטה לא מיקניא mah amah ivriyah
be-perutah lo mikanya so the same way by אמה עבריה amah ivriyah
it's not a פרוטה perutah because as we said it had to
be a higher amount so that you could reduce it. אף אשה
בפרוטה לא מיקניא af ishah be-perutah lo mikanya same by marriage of
a woman. So now the גמרא Gemara says אימא פלגא דדינרא eima
palga de-dinara so so what say half a דינר? dinar? אימא שתי
פרוטות eima shtei perutot or say two פרוטות perutot right? There's a
lot of numbers between 1 and 192. Okay I think there are
191 numbers 190 numbers between them. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara says
okay no כיון דאפיקתיה מפרוטה אוקמה אדינר keivan de-afiktaih mi-perutah okmah a-dinar
nah once it's more than a פרוטה perutah we're going to go
to like the next serious coinage which will be a דינר. dinar.
All right now I don't know again I don't know why a
מעה ma'ah isn't serious but okay. Like look think about this. If
I say it can't be a penny right so and I said
all right so fine it's a dollar. Now you go a dollar's
a hundred times a penny. What about a nickel? How about a
dime? How about a quarter? So you could say no like the
next serious you know sort of if what's it
called like a order of magnitude you know the next serious sort
of category is going up from a penny to a dollar. So
you go up from a פרוטה perutah to a דינר. dinar. Sure
there's something else you know there's even a silver thing besides that
but that makes sense as the next stage. All right so that's
the explanation. It has to be more than a פרוטה perutah and
once we know it's more than a פרוטה perutah we're going to
establish it at a דינר dinar you know that's how we learn
it out. Okay that's that's one a new explanation for בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this okay רבא אמר היינו טעמא דבית שמאי Rava amar hainu ta'ama
de-Beit Shammai a third reason for בית שמאי Beit Shammai one is
the presumption women won't agree to less than a דינר. dinar. Number
two is if it's not going to be a פרוטה perutah it's
the next serious level of coinage which is a דינר. dinar. And
רבא Rava says you know what here's the reason שלא יהו בנות
ישראל כהפקר she-lo yehu benot Yisrael ke-hefker not about the woman's subjective
desire but more about a societal concern. If we allow a woman
to be purchased for a פרוטה perutah it sends a
a message that they're like you know garbage right you know penny.
So it's sort of that's you know that and it leads to
a mistreatment of women to a devaluing of of women in society.
So again it's funny because again you could argue that if it's
a פרוטה perutah like I said before that if it's a פרוטה
perutah it's clearly symbolic. If it's a דינר dinar it's more you
know it's
more maybe evokes the idea of purchase but not really you know
sometimes in context they say I think I mentioned this before like
in consideration for one dollar you know I obligate myself to it.
Doesn't say in consideration for one penny. Right? You could have something
that's symbolic and still is it a you know it's like a
or also like I said yesterday it's like it's not you know
you know it's not the gift that matters it's the thought that
counts. Yeah but like if this is the thought you put into
it you know if it's so it could be even if it's
symbolic the symbolism of a penny is a degrading type of a
symbolism. The symbolism of a dollar you know is a little bit
more substantial.
So and that's what רבא Rava says. Now the problem still here
is is that that's a nice type of a sort of a
societal reason a policy reason to do it but it doesn't explain
a דאורייתא de-Oraita idea about why that would be. So if you
look at רש"י Rashi רש"י Rashi says כהפקר ke-hefker רש"י Rashi about
six lines down in the narrow
lines רש"י Rashi says לקנות liknos בדבר מועט be-davar muat ומדרבנן הוא
דקאמרי לה בית שמאי. u-mi-derabbanan hu de-ka'amri lah Beit Shammai. the rabbis
technically a פרוטה peruta should work מן התורה, min haTorah, but the
rabbis prevented it from working anything less than a דינר dinar for
the sake of protecting the status of women. It wouldn't, it would
be invalid because אפקעינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה. afkinu rabbanan lekiddushin minei.
Yeah, whatever, exactly, okay.
So that's so and
quite fascinating that the גמרא Gemara is reading this as to protect
the status of women, right? So in this right, if you hold
it up exactly in contrast with what we said a second ago,
which is בית שמאי's Beis Shammai reason was because they learned out
from the sale of an אמה עבריה, amah ivriyah, right? There's some
aspects of the ways of thinking about marriage which very much seems
to treat a woman totally as property to be bought and sold.
And here we're saying almost the exact opposite, you know, that it's
done דוקא davka to protect the status of women. Yeah, Charlie, what
did you want to say?
Some fancy people will take a salary of dollar a year to
serve and never take one cent.
Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, so that's בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai.
Now to בית הלל. Beis Hillel. בית הלל Beis Hillel says בפרוטה.
Be'peruta. Now, now we're back to בית הלל's Beis Hillel פרוטה. peruta.
Now פרוטה peruta remember we said was one eighth of an איסר
האיטלקי. issar ha'italki. There's your איסר. issar. Okay, so, we saw רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says למימרא פרוטה כל שהוא. Lema're peruta kolshehu. רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says we say a פרוטה peruta whatever its value
might be in a given society at a given time, even if
it changes, fluctuates in value.
אביי Abaye said, והא לכתני כמה היא פרוטה אחד משמונה באיסר האיטלקי?
V'ha laktani kama hi peruta echad mishmoneh be'issar italki? אביי Abaye said,
wait a minute, there's the משנה mishna went out of its way
to say one eighth of an איסר. issar. So clearly an absolute
value wanted to be very specific, clearly to tell you that it's
not something that you go at any society at any given time.
וכי תימא הני מילי בדורו של משה, Vekhi teima hani milei bedoro
shel moshe, maybe that was telling you at the time of משה,
Moshe, one imagines there was no Italian איסר issars at the time
of משה. Moshe. It's funny the גמרא Gemara didn't say בדורו של
רבי, bedoro shel rebbe, but again we're presumably learning it out from
a פסוק pasuk in the תורה. Torah. Okay, I mean, you know,
the תורה Torah says כסף kesef we mean minimum כסף. kesef. So
maybe that's what was minimum in the time of משה. Moshe. Okay,
that's like the original amount.
אבל הכא בדידחשיבו
להו לאינשי, Aval hacha bedichashvu lehu le'inshei, but basically now we would
go to whatever has that analogous weight for people, like the minimum
coinage for people. Again, it's particularly funny since the גמרא Gemara is
dealing with the possibility that there isn't a fixed amount, that it
basically means whatever is the minimum amount that's considered money in a
given society. So it didn't have to be של משה. shel moshe.
משה Moshe could have been a different coin. It's really is funny
the גמרא Gemara didn't say, you know, why didn't the גמרא Gemara
say, you know, בדורו של רבי, bedoro shel rebbe, right? Because the
whole point is that we don't have to say it's the same
as it was in the time of משה, Moshe, that the משנה
mishna is telling for its time what the minimum coinage is, and
the הלכה halakha really is for any society and for any time
we'll determine whatever a פרוטה peruta is. Okay, so that's the point,
maybe the משנה mishna doesn't lock us in. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no. והא כי אתא רב דימי אמר, V'ha ki asa Rav
Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael he said, שיער רבי סימאי בדורו כמה היא פרוטה אחד משמונה
באיסר האיטלקי. shi'er Rabbi Simai bedoro kama hi peruta echad mishmoneh be'issar
italki. So רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai assessed in his generation based on
this idea of one eighth of an Italian איסר. issar. What does
that mean? רש"י Rashi explains it means that somebody married a woman
with an איסר, issar, and רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai wanted to determine
was she really married or not. And what he had to do
was he had to assess is the איסר issar that she was
married with as, not איסר, issar, excuse me, a פרוטה. peruta. He
marries this woman with a פרוטה peruta and he had to determine
if she was married and he had to assess is this פרוטה
peruta in our generation still worth one eighth of an Italian איסר.
issar. So he was using the standard in the משנה mishna to
determine
whether the פרוטה peruta of his time was considered a פרוטה peruta
or not. How much is it today? I don't know. So you
see, I don't know, five cents, ten cents, certainly a dollar is
way more. Okay, anyway, so
you see that you go by, you don't go by every, it's
not a subjective or it's not a standard that changes based on
circumstances or based on society and time, it's an objective standard. וכי
אתא רבין, V'ki asa Ravin, similarly when רבין Ravin came, אמר, amar,
he said, רבי דוסתאי ורבי ינאי ורבי אושעיא, Rabbi Dostai v'Rabbi Yannai
v'Rabbi Oshaya, these three great rabbis, שיערו כמה הוי פרוטה אחד מששה
באיסר האיטלקי. shi'eru kama havai peruta echad mishishah be'issar italki. Now when
they, now this is interesting, it's against the משנה, mishna, we're going
to get back to it. But nevertheless, the point for us is
they were using an objective standard. A man married a woman with
a פרוטה peruta and they wanted to determine was she really married
or not and had to decide was it more or less than
one sixth of an איסר. issar. So you see a פרוטה peruta
is not we don't say any פרוטה peruta in any society is
enough, it has to meet an objective
consistent standard. Now we're going to get to what their debate is
based on, but first we're making this point that it does not
change based on society and time. There's an objective consistent standard. One
minute. אמר ליה רב יוסף אי הכי, Amar lei Rav Yosef ei
hachi, one minute. I got a problem. If so. We're saying that
a פרוטה prutah always is an eighth or maybe a sixth of
an Italian איסר, issar, explain to me the following משנה. Mishnah. היינו
דתנינא, Hainu detanina, how do we teach the following thing here, actually
I think it's not a משנה, Mishnah, it's a something in the,
yeah, it is a
משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
so צא וחשוב, tse vachashov, or actually no, it's a what do
you call it, it's a ספרא. Sifra. Okay, we teach the following
in the ספרא. Sifra. צא וחשוב כמה פרוטות בשני סלעים. Tse vachashov
kama prutos beshnei sla'im. Now, if somebody is נהנה, neheneh, does מעילה,
me'ilah, gets, derives benefit from הקדש, hekdesh, they have to bring an
אשם. asham. And the תורה Torah says the אשם, asham, how much
is the אשם asham worth? כסף שקלים, Kesef shekalim, two שקל. shekel.
Okay, a שקל shekel is a סלע. sela. Okay, now, here's the
point that the ספרא Sifra is making is, you benefited, you got
a פרוטה's prutah worth of benefit, a penny's worth of benefit. You're
going to have to bring a קרבן korban worth two שקל. shekel.
Like so look at how weighty your sin was and how disproportionate
it is. So we want to point out how much more your
קרבן korban is going to cost than how much you, than you
know, how much you benefited. Now a שקל shekel is 768, right,
פרוטות. prutos. So basically your קרבן korban is going to cost about
1500, you know, 1550 roughly whatever, you know, 1550, 1500 times the
amount that you benefited. Okay now but he says but one minute.
I don't, but I don't understand cause look at what the ספרא
Sifra says. צא וחשוב, Tse vachashov, go and figure out, כמה פרוטות
בשני סלעים. kama prutos beshnei sla'im. How many פרוטות prutos oh, it's
two שקל, shekel, בכסף שקלים. bechesef shekalim. Okay, so this would have
to be 15, right, I did that, I did it. 1500, right.
Okay, so
יותר מאלפיים, yoser mealpayim, more than 2,000. Now one minute, we just
did the math and we only got 1500 or spare change. So
the גמרא Gemara says, השתא אלפיים לא הוין, hashta alpayim lo havyan,
it's not even 2,000, יותר מאלפיים קרי להו, yoser mealpayim kari lehu,
you call them more than 2,000? So from the fact that this
ספרא Sifra calls it more than 2,000 you see that the value
of פרוטות prutos can change, that's his argument. That the ספרא Sifra
must have been dealing with a פרוטה prutah that was worth much
less than, than you know this one eighth here. Okay, so I
remember this from,
I read the תוספות Tosafos yesterday. Anyway, he says look, פרוטות prutos
don't have a consistent value, this ספרא Sifra thinks it's more than
2,000 and it's really only more than 1500 and it's really only
about 1500. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר להו ההוא סבא, amar lehu hahu saba, or a certain old
person said to him, no, אנא תנינא לה, ana tninah lah, I
taught that ברייתא, Braisa, and here's the way I have the גרסא
girsa of the ברייתא. Braisa. קרוב לאלפיים, Karov lealpayim, it's not more
than 2,000, it's close to 2,000. גמרא Gemara says, סוף סוף, sof
sof, what do you mean close to 2,000? Do the math. אלף
וחמש מאות, Elef vechameish meos, it's 1500, ושלושים ושישה, veshloshim veshishah, and
36, okay, 1536. You can sort of see that, right? 14, 13,
right, 2, right, 1536. הוה דהוין. hudu dehavyan. So that's not close
to 2,000, it's almost 500 away. גמרא Gemara says no,
כיון דנפקו מפלגא, keivan denafku mipalga, קרוב לאלפיים קרי ליה, karov lealpayim
kari lei, since it's over 1500, so you round to the nearest
thousand. Okay, so 1536 rounds to the nearest thousand, that's close to
2,000. All right, anyway, exactly.
All right, so anyway, people do like. So we solved that problem.
But the goal, but the point was to prove is פרוטה prutah
always the same value? Okay, and that seemed to say no, but
we solved it. Now let's get back to this issue, we are
going to say there's a consistent amount that we determine halachically a
פרוטה prutah about, and it does not change based on society and
time. But there's still this debate about one sixth versus one eighth
of an איסר. issar. Let's try to figure out what that's based
on. גופא, Gufa, let's go back and look at that debate. כי
אתא רב דימי אמר שיער רבי סימאי בדורו כמה היא פרוטה אחד
משמונה באיסר איטלקי. Ki ata Rav Dimi amar shieir Rabbi Simai bedoro
kama hi prutah echad mishmonah beissar italki. כי אתא רבין אמר שיערו
רבי יוסי ורבי יהודה ורבי אושעיא כמה היא פרוטה אחד מששה באיסר
איטלקי. Ki ata Ravin amar shieiru Rabbi Yosi veRabbi Yehudah veRabbi Oshayah
kama hi prutah echad meshishah beissar italki. So אמר ליה אביי לרב
דימי, amar lei Abaye leRav Dimi, נימא את ורבין, neima at veRavin,
maybe this debate between you and רבין Ravin about whether it's an
eighth or a sixth, בפלוגתא דהני תנאי קמיפלגי, bipligta dehanei tannai kamifligi,
you debate, it's the same debate as we find amongst these תנאים.
Tannaim. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa,
פרוטה שאמרו חכמים, prutah sheamru chachamim, the פרוטה prutah that the חכמים
chachamim spoke about, אחד משמונה באיסר איטלקי, echad mishmonah beissar italki, one
eighth of an Italian איסר. issar. Now, we're going to do the
whole math. שש מעות כסף דינר, Shesh maos kesef dinar, okay, a
דינר dinar is six, right, you see I have 32 here and
192 here, okay, so, so this is one, if we're measuring מעה
maah here, right, it's one מעה maah to six of these, right?
Everybody's here with me with math? Right, you see this is 32,
this was 192 in פרוטות, prutos, one to six ratio, okay. So
there are שש מעות shesh maos sort of working backwards. Okay, but
there are שש מעות shesh maos for every
דינר. dinar.
מעה שני פונדיון, Maah shenei pundyon, a מעה maah is two פונדיון,
pundyon, okay, פונדיון שני איסרין, pundyon shenei issarin, a פונדיון pundyon is
two איסר, issar, right, I already have this sort of here. Okay,
and an איסר שני מסומסין, issar shenei musmasin, we don't have that,
מסומס שני קונטוס. musmas shenei kuntos.
קונטרק שתי פרוטות. Kuntrak shetei perutot. Okay, anyway, there's some smaller coinages
within here. There's a nickel and a dime and whatever, but anyway,
it's a one to eight. Okay, so this is exactly the things
what we have, you know? And you basically do this, you know,
you do this times six times two whatever and it's a one
to one hundred and ninety-two ratio. Okay, fine. נמצא פרוטה אחד משמונה
באיסר איטלקי. Nimtsa prutah echad mishmoneh be'isar italki. Now
really the only part you needed at the end was when it
went from an איסר isar to it, you know, it's half, it's
twice of this and twice of this and whatever twice of that,
so it's one-eighth. A פרוטה prutah is one-eighth of an Italian איסר.
isar. So that position says it's one-eighth of an Italian איסר. isar.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, now רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel has a different set of
coinages. You have to imagine living in the system where you have
competing systems of coinage going around.
Like today, in different countries, you know, the Euro, the dollar.
Yeah, but I don't think it was only that, I think it
was ממש mamash like same time, same place. Anyway, like there was
a local coinage and a whatever, anyway. שלושה
הדריסין למעה. Shelosha hadrasin lema'ah. Okay, now he's going to say actually
there are, I agree to this one to six ratio, okay, let's
sort of do it in the opposite direction. One דינר dinar is
six מעה. ma'ah. That I agree. But then there's going to be
something called a הדראס hadras or whatever here, and we're figuring out
how much a דינר dinar is worth. And a הדראס, hadras, there
are three, that's a three to one. So it's going to be
eighteen הדריסין, hadrasin, right? Three, three הדראס hadras per מעה. ma'ah. שני
הנצים להדראס. Shenei hanatzim lahadras. So now we have a הנץ, hanatz,
so there's going to be two to two there, so it's thirty-six.
We're figuring out how many, you know, in a, in a, in
a דינר, dinar, right? So there's six מעה ma'ah in a דינר,
dinar, this is a three to one ratio, there are eighteen הדריסין,
hadrasin, there are thirty-six
הנצים. hanatzim. שני שמנים להנץ. Shenei shemanim lahanatz. Okay, so then there's
this thing called a שמן, sheman, I don't know, anyway we're up
to seventy-two, that's two to
one. שני פרוטות לשמנים. Shenei perutot leshemanim. And then we get to
פרוטה prutah where it is one hundred and forty-four. Okay? So according
to this, the relevance of this is, people were sort of seeing
what I was doing here, the relevance of this is according to
this, there's one hundred and forty-four פרוטות perutot to a דינר, dinar,
not one hundred and ninety-two פרוטות perutot to a דינר. dinar. Okay?
Now, if you want to figure out, okay, so, okay,
so what?
Now, yes. So נמצא פרוטה אחד משישה באיסר איטלקי. Nimtsa prutah echad
mishishah be'isar italki. So if we're assuming the ratio of איסר isar
to דינר dinar is the same, this is a one to twenty-four
ratio. Right? See that twenty-four? Eight times twenty-four is, I mean eight
times twenty-five would give you two hundred, right? So this is a
one to twenty-four ratio. Okay, so if there are twenty-four איסר isar
for a דינר dinar and now according to this, a דינר dinar
is one hundred and forty-four פרוטות, perutot, okay,
so twenty-four into one hundred and forty-four is six. Six פרוטות perutot
for an איסר. isar. Alright? So this person has, according to this
figuring, okay, we've got six פרוטות perutot to an איסר. isar. So
you see says that seems to be a debate. Are there six
פרוטות perutot to an איסר isar or are there eight פרוטות perutot
to an איסר? isar? Okay, one wonders how could this be a
debate? Like the government must know, I mean there must be a
reality out there. Okay, anyway, so לימא דמר כתנא קמא ורבין דאמר
כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Leima d'mar ke-Tanna Kamma ve-Ravin d'amar ke-Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. Let's say this is exactly your debate, which could be
fine, makes sense, but who wants to be like a דעת יחיד?
da'at yachid? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he says no, בין דידי
בין דרבין אליבא דתנא קמא. bein didi bein de-Ravin aliba de-Tanna Kamma.
We're both agreeing with the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says one
to eight. So how could I, I said one to six, how
could I be saying one to eight? ולא קשיא הא דאיקרא
איסורי הא דזולא איסורי. Ve-lo kashya, ha de-ikra isurei, ha de-zula isurei.
Okay, basically what he is saying is the following. Now I can't
figure this out, I can only figure this out if we assume
that an איסר isar and a פרוטה prutah were made from, from
different metals. Okay, an איסר isar and a פרוטה prutah were made
from different metals. Okay, I actually looked it up. The original איסר
isar they say they think they know is some, they think it's
something called an as which actually was like a very widespread coinage
in the Roman realm, actually in, it was based on a Greek
coin, so that's נמצא פרוטה אחד משמונה באיסר איטלקי. Nimtsa prutah echad
mishmoneh be'isar italki. Anyway,
the original one was bronze, actually, and a פרוטה prutah was copper.
So actually you could have three metals going on here. Okay, although
it does say that by the time of the, you know, like
by the time the משנה Mishna was being written, they had already
made this into copper. So it's all, it was all the same,
it was all the same metal. So what I'm about to say
doesn't make sense but anyway, I mean I can't understand the גמרא.
Gemara. The only way I'm going to understand what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is if they were of different metals. Here's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to assume. The amount of פרוטות perutot to
דינר dinar is stable, okay? It's always one hundred and ninety-two פרוטות
perutot to a דינר. dinar. So, you know, again you'd have to
assume, meaning I guess what's, what's challenging me is I'm assuming that
the coinage is always based on the weight of the precious metal
and it's not just a nominal amount. And actually from the little
reading I did last
night... It actually seems that even in the time of the Roman
Republic, coins could have a nominal value which was higher than their
pure metal value. So that might also be how this makes sense.
But for now anyway, wow, I didn't know it was that early.
Yeah, so anyway, assuming that there's a fixed ratio of 192 פרוטות
Perutot to a דינר, Dinar, the גמרא Gemara is going to assume
that that ratio is fixed. But what is not
fixed is the ratio of the איסר Issar to the פרוטה. Peruta.
That can fluctuate based on the value of the איסר. Issar. Okay.
So here's what it's going to
say. Where were we? בין רבנן אליבא דתנא קמא. Bein Rabbanan Aliba
DeTanna Kama. We all agree like the תנא קמא. Tanna Kama. 192
פרוטות Perutot to a
דינר. Dinar. ולא קשיא. Velo Kashya. הא דאיקור איסורי הא דזול איסורי.
Ha De'ikur Issarei Ha Dezul Issarei. Is the איסר? Issar? Does that
have a higher value or a lower value in a given time
in society or whatever? And by the way, the איסר's Issar value
did fluctuate radically over time. Like there was a time where it
was basically worth like, I think, like a 20th of what its
original worth was. Anyway, הא דאיקור איסורי Ha De'ikur Issarei קום עשרין
וארבעה בזוזא. Kum Esrin Ve'arba'a Bezuzza. If the איסר Issar is of
a higher value, then there are
24 איסרין Issarin to a דינר. Dinar. A דינר Dinar is a
זוז. Zuz. Okay, so this is a 1 to 24 ratio, right?
8 to 192 is a 1 to 24
ratio. And when it's a 1 to 24 ratio, this is a
1 to 8 ratio. Because again, the פרוטה Peruta to דינר Dinar
is stable. Okay, so when this is 1 to 24, then that's
1 to 8. One minute. הא דזול, Ha Dezul, if however the
איסר Issar is devalued in a particular time, is of a lesser
value, תלתין ותרין בזוזא, Taltin Vetarin Bezuzza, then this would be a
1 to 32 ratio. Then this would be, right, 6? Right, so
6, right, is a 1 to 32. So what we're saying is
a פרוטה's Peruta value never changes. A פרוטה's Peruta value is stable
vis-à-vis the דינר, Dinar, which would also I guess be a very
stable value. So if I'm one time I'm going to describe it
as one eighth of an איסר Issar and somebody else is going
to describe it as one sixth, we're not really debating the value
of the פרוטה. Peruta. What we're really debating is the value of
the איסר. Issar. The איסר's Issar value fluctuates, but the דינר's Dinar
value and the פרוטה's Peruta value are relatively stable. Okay, so that's
his answer. Yes, Michael.
So my question is then, everyone's agreeing though that you couldn't just
like take out of more modern times, take out a penny and
say, okay I'm koshered leave because a penny is less than a
פרוטה. Peruta.
So they're saying you
can't use the smallest coin of the realm. It always has to
be the value of the פרוטה. Peruta. And what we're saying is
the value of the פרוטה Peruta basically being figured
as 1/192nd of the value of a דינר. Dinar. Now the question
is, by value do we mean
the buying value of that, or do we mean the precious metal
value of that? Right? So that's the whole question. Anyway, I would
also say talking about devaluing, I want to say something which is,
oh look! That's up there from two months ago. So this is
actually an excellent point to make. So remember that דינר Dinar is
a זוז. Zuz. And a כתובה Ketubah is 200 זוז. Zuz. Now
200 זוז Zuz used to be enough to support yourself basically for
like a year, or maybe even two years. Okay, that's 200 זוז.
Zuz. Now how much was 200 זוז? Zuz? If you know our
current כתובות Ketubot don't say, they say 200 זוז Zuz but they
have מאתיים זקוקים Matayim Zekukim of כסף Kesef צרוף, Tzaruf, of pure
silver. A זקוק Zekuk is a much, much larger amount than a
זוז. Zuz. And basically what happened was in the Middle Ages 200
זוזים Zuzim were worth almost nothing, and the woman was therefore not
being protected by the כתובה. Ketubah. So what they did is
they established as a תקנה Takkana that all כתובות, Ketubot, every חתן
Chatan has to basically assign the dowry value at 100 זקוק Zekuk
and the תוספת Tosefet value at 100 זקוק. Zekuk. So a woman
was promised 200 זקוק, Zekuk, which was much, much more than 200
זוז. Zuz. Now these are weights, and actually there's a very precise
weight that we have going back to ancient times, which is essentially
like I think like barley weight or whatever,
anyway, it's a very precise weight. So actually the 200 זוז Zuz
is a measure of a weight of silver. Okay. So the presumption
is it's not based on buying power, it's based on the precious
metal value, and it's based on a weight of silver. By the
time of the Middle Ages, or by nowadays, 200 זוז Zuz is
approximately $600. Okay, 200 זוז, Zuz, which means that a זוז Zuz
is $3. Okay. And so which means that a פרוטה Peruta is
about, do the math, about a penny and a half. Okay, maybe
two pennies. Okay. So therefore whereas 200 זקוק Zekuk is $27,000
roughly in today's price of silver. Okay. So that's the 200 זקוק
Zekuk of the כתובה Ketubah is
$27,000. But that used to be... but זוז Zuz used to be
a lot more. זוז Zuz used to be approximately that. So nowadays...
days, based on the value of a דינר, dinar, which is about
$2, which is about $3 is the value of a דינר, dinar,
okay? A פרוטה pruta is about two cents, okay? But it could
have been—but put your two cents in—but it could have been, right,
that what do you call it, that
you know, originally it was closer to $2 or closer to a
dollar. Okay, so it might have been originally a dollar, but we
don't go by the buying power. We go by precious metal value.
So
anyway, so when I say to somebody, "Does it look like it's
worth a פרוטה?" pruta? You know, I don't give the exact amount,
but if somebody were to push me, I say a dollar because
clearly a פרוטה pruta nowadays is much less than a dollar. But
originally it might have been closer to a dollar or $2.
And this is not just a debate for כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin,
it's applied as we said for everything else, meaning the position's applied.
Right,
presumably that is correct. Right, that seems to be the גמרא's Gemara
pace. Anytime we discuss פרוטה, pruta, we do not mean the smallest
coin of the realm, we mean a פרוטה. pruta. Although nowadays again,
that's close to a penny, it's maybe two cents. But originally it
was probably closer to a dollar.
But I can't take five שקל shekel and פדיון pidyon my firstborn
son. I mean I can't take five Israeli שקלים shekalim and פדיון.
pidyon. Correct, correct. Yeah, obviously. How much weight is this זקוק? zokuk?
A זקוק, zokuk, yeah, I'd have to check, I mean, but yeah.
So what do we write in the כתובה ksuva now?
We write you get 200 זוז zuz for your מוהר mohar and
100 זקוק zokuk for the price we just assessed the dowry at,
which means that that's the price that if she gets divorced he's
going to have to give her back because he's declaring that her
dowry is worth 100 זקוק, zokuk, and 100 זקוק zokuk for תוספת,
tosefet, which is the additional amount that he's agreed to give even
though he's not obligated. So bottom line is what she would take
out in the case of divorce would be 200 זקוק, zokuk, okay?
All right.
What do you mean by we go by the precious metal value,
not the market?
Meaning
we don't say how much could a דינר dinar have bought in
the time of חז"ל. Chazal. First of all, you know, the talk
like its consumer price index, like first of all, what do you
mean bought? Are we talking about how much food, how much bread,
how much meat, how much real estate, right? And then you try
to assess, well, what's an equivalent buying power nowadays. But that's a
very hard measure and it's a different measure. We basically go by,
like, precious metal value. Yeah.
The value of gold and silver plummeted in the 16th century when
the Spanish colonized the New World and opened the mines...
But this was already in, like, the 12th or 13th century.
Yeah, I was wondering, did was there any adjustment made in early
modern?
I don't know. Okay, so let's continue. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. Now we move on to a slightly, I mean, whatever, slightly
different point. We don't have to worry about all these numbers.
Okay. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, קידשה בתמרא, kiddasha bitmara, if a man
married a woman with a date,
אפילו עומד כור תמרין בדינר, afilu omid kor tmarin bedinar, even if
an entire כור, kor, you know, which is a huge quantity of
תמרין tmarin are going for a דינר, dinar, which would mean that
presumably there's more than 200 dates in a כור, kor, okay? So
that means it's clearly that a date is worth less than a
פרוטה. pruta. Nevertheless, מקודשת, mekudeshet, she's married. Why? It's based on the
market rate of תמרין, tmarin, it's clearly worth less than a פרוטה.
pruta. חיישינן שמא שווה פרוטה במדי. Chashinan shema shaveh pruta bemadai. Maybe
there's some country somewhere off
in מדי, Madai, somewhere, you know, in פרס ומדי, Paras uMadai, somewhere
halfway around the world, maybe
this goes for a פרוטה. pruta. Which is so funny because now
we say, okay, פרוטה's pruta a fixed amount. But when you do
it with something that's not money but some object, how do you
assess its value? So of course we would have assumed you assess
it based on the value here, right? And שמואל Shmuel is introducing
this wild idea that if somewhere on the globe it's worth a
פרוטה, pruta, maybe that is enough to give it significance. Okay, so
let's take a look. ותנן, Ve'anan tenan, בית הלל אומרים בפרוטה ובשווה
פרוטה, Beis Hillel omri bipruta ubishaveh pruta, the equivalent of a פרוטה.
pruta. And according to שמואל, Shmuel, you would never be able to
assess that something was or wasn't the equivalent of a פרוטה pruta
because you'd always have to be worried about what's it worth in
מדי. Madai. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, הא בקידושי ודאי
הא בקידושי ספק. Lo kashya ha bekidushei vadai ha bekidushei safek. Yes,
what בית הלל Beis Hillel is saying is, if it's worth a
פרוטה pruta here in this locale, then she's ודאי vadai married. If
it's not worth a פרוטה pruta in this locale, she's ספק safek
married. So we always thought בית הלל Beis Hillel was saying if
it's not worth a פרוטה pruta she's ודאי vadai not married.
It's saying if it's not worth a פרוטה pruta she's ספק safek
married. If it is worth a פרוטה pruta she's ודאי vadai married.
This is a huge חומרא, chumra, right? All right, because every case
is a ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin. ההוא גברא דאקדיש בזוודא דאורדיסא, Hu
gavra de’akdish bezavda de’ordisa, a certain man married a woman with a
like a bundle, רש"י Rashi says of like, I don't know, cloth,
a like, you know, of pieces of cloth. שמאטעס Shmattes essentially. שמאטעס
Shmattes essentially. יתיב רב סימי בר חייא קמיה דרב וקא מעיין בה.
Yasiv Rav Simi bar Chiya kamei deRav veka me’ayen bah. So he
was sitting in front of רב Rav and he was looking into
the case. אי ביה שווה פרוטה אין אי לא לא. Is beih
shaveh pruta in lo lo. If it was worth a פרוטה pruta
she's married, if not, no. The גמרא Gemara says, now again, if
a פרוטה prutah was a penny or two pennies, it’s hard to
imagine what’s less than that. But if it was a dollar, you
could imagine something like that would be worth less than a dollar.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי לית בה שוה פרוטה לא? Ve'ei
leis bei shaveh prutah la? How, even if it was not a
פרוטה, prutah, how could you say it’s not a concern? דאמר שמואל
חיישינן, De'amar Shmuel chaishinan, but even less than a פרוטה, prutah, ספק
קידושין. safek kidushin. לא קשיא lo kashya, הא בקידושי ודאי הא בקידושי
ספק. ha bekiddushei vadai ha bekiddushei safek. Okay, and so what? You
want to know, is she definitely married or is she ספק safek
married? So now the גמרא's Gemara introducing that every case of less
than a פרוטה prutah would still turn her into a ספק safek
married. Another story, we’ll see if we end this way. ההוא גברא
דאקדש באבנא דכוחלא, Hahu gavra de'akdish be'avna dechuchla,
a man married a woman with like a stone of a, you
know, one of those like colored stones, I don’t know what's, what
do they define what, what it is? The blue?
What? A mood ring? Yeah, something like that.
שישא שחור דאבנא דכוחלא. Shisha shachor de'avna dechuchla. What? Like black marble?
Yeah, no, but you know how you go sometimes and they sell
all these colored stones and you can get like, you know, you
can get like a whole like whatever, like a bag full of
them for five dollars. So you have these things, they look pretty,
they're colored stones, but each one of them is not worth a
lot. We're not talking about, you know, diamonds and emeralds. Okay, exactly.
Okay, so he married a woman with this stone.
יתיב רב חסדא וקא משער לה. Yativ Rav Chisda veka mesha'eir lah.
He was estimating. אי אית בה שוה פרוטה אין ואי לא לא.
Ei it bah shaveh prutah in ve'ei lo lo. If it was
a שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah she’s married, if not, not. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואי לית בה שוה פרוטה לא, Ve'ei leis bei
shaveh prutah lo, והאמר שמואל חיישינן? veha'amar Shmuel chaishinan? Doesn't שמואל Shmuel
say that we doubt, we have it as a ספק קידושין? safek
kidushin? So finally the גמרא Gemara here puts the brakes on שמואל.
Shmuel. The גמרא Gemara says, רב חסדא לא סבר לה דשמואל. Rav
Chisda lo savar lah deShmuel. Rather than saying the alternative would have
been ספק קידושין, safek kidushin, and רש"י Rashi says the reasons why
we didn't say that but I don't want to go into it.
Anyway, it says, you know what? רב חסדא Rav Chisda doesn't hold
of שמואל. Shmuel. Okay. אמרה ליה אימיה, Amrah lei immeih, so now
the mother, or some have the גירסא girsa אמא, emma, the mother
of the woman who was given this thing said, דההוא יומא דקדשה
הוה ביה שוה פרוטה. Dehahu yoma dekadshah havah bei shaveh prutah. So
now we've established, if it’s less than a פרוטה, prutah, we don't
hold of שמואל, Shmuel, if it’s less than a פרוטה, prutah, she’s
ודאי אינה מקודשת. vadai eina mekudeshet. Now the mother, and now of
course the question I’m waiting for somebody to ask me is why
doesn't he just now give her, if they both still want the
marriage, why doesn't he just now give her another thing that's worth
a פרוטה? prutah? So
רש"י Rashi says describe, maybe one of them wants to back out,
but רש"י Rashi also describes the case similarly that she already accepted
קידושין kidushin from another man. Okay, exactly. So anyway, so the mother
now says, either the groom’s mother or the bride’s mother said, on
the wedding day, I am telling you that the market, you know,
I saw him go to the store and buy it or whatever,
it was worth more than a פרוטה. prutah. Okay, you don't have
to figure out now you’re trying to assess what its value is
today, I’m telling you when they got married,
it was worth a
פרוטה, prutah, הוה ביה שוה פרוטה. havah bei shaveh prutah. אמר לה
לאו כל כמינך דאסרת לה אבתרא. Amar lah lav kol kaminach de'asrat
lah abatra. So
he said to her,
you are not believed to make her forbidden for the second guy.
Okay, meaning you know why? That's
just a, you know, it’s a testimony of one person, of a
woman who is not, עד אחד ed echad is not, but this
isn't איסורים, issurim, this is עריות, arayos, אשת איש eishes ish and
so on. And he basically, well no, anyway, and he says I’m
dismissing that, you know, you’re just one witness, a woman’s testimony is
not given the same weight, we're dismissing that. Okay, now what’s the
evidence that we can dismiss that? And the point is it impacts
other people. You read נוגע בעדות, nogei'a eidut, it’s also why it’s
not just איסורים, issurim, it impacts the second man, right? So it’s
not just a question of like a כשרות kashrus issue which really
just affects me. Okay, so anyway, he dismissed... no, it doesn't matter,
but you're taking away, you know, you’re challenging the fact, you know,
his rights as it were.
What if he doesn't mean to give a גט get then?
If we determined it was ודאי, vadai, well no, I mean if
we determined it was ודאי vadai less than a פרוטה prutah then
he would say, right? I mean that would be the interesting thing,
and we’re going to see that. If the assessment right now is
that it’s ודאי vadai less than a פרוטה, prutah, and he determines
based on the information he has at his disposal that it's less
than a פרוטה prutah now, and he's assuming that it was less
than a פרוטה prutah at the time of the marriage, because that’s
really what matters, but that's his assessment he arrives at. And somebody
says, this mother says no, I’m telling you it was a פרוטה,
prutah, and he totally dismisses her. He’s going to come to the
conclusion that she ודאי vadai was not married to the first guy,
does not need a גט, get, and is ודאי vadai married to
the second guy. Right, so exactly, so you’re right, it is being
immediately lenient. He's completely dismissing the testimony. Now what on what basis?
He says,
לא מאי ניהו דיהודית דבתסותיה דרבי חייא. La mai nihu deYehudis devatsusei
deRabbi Chiya. It’s similar to the story of יהודית, Yehudis, the wife
of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. דהוה לה צער לידה. Dahavah lah tza'ar
leidah. She would have a lot of anguish in childbirth. Okay, and
she had a lot of twins, רש"י Rashi points out. אמרה ליה,
Amrah lei, so she said to her husband one of these times
that she had all of this anguish, like she thought even like
descended about like what is she doing, like what did she do
to be suffering this much? So she said... know why what I
think this is because of? Because אמר לי אם, Amar Li Em,
because my mother told me כי בה אבוך קדושי כי זוטרי Keeve
Bi Chavuch Kidushei Kee Zutres that your father actually had married me
off to another man when I was under age. So here she
was, she was married to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, by this one
of these like major אמוראים, Amoraim, and all of a sudden ten
years into marriage after she's having this pains in childbirth she says,
you know what? Maybe this is because I'm really married to another
man! Cause my mother told me that my father had married me
off to another man when I was a baby. So what is
so so so what happened? So so so he says אמר לה,
Amar Lah, so her husband said to her, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
yes, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, לאו כל כמינך דאימך, Lav Kol Keminach
De'imach, your mother has no believability, דאסרת ליך עלוואי, De'asrat Lich Alavai,
that she should make you forbidden to me. Okay, so I that
that testimony has absolutely no halakhic weight. Okay, it's not two witnesses,
etc., no halakhic weight. So here too, no halakhic weight. Even though
you'll say, oh my God, he's sleeping with an אשת איש! Eishes
Ish! Isn't he concerned that his wife is married to another man?
No, those we completely dismiss it, we assess it based on the
evidence we have at our disposal. There's actually a story I gotta
tell you, this is actually a joke but I'll tell you that
one later. But there's a story that a man said, somebody told
me this story about the guy he knew, a rabbi was being
מסדר קידושין Mesader Kiddushin and under the חופה Chuppah the חתן Chosson
gives you know says to the rabbi, he says, you know, this
is the ring that my grandmother, you know, gave me. And my
grandmother said it was very, very important that I use this ring
and that I show it to the rabbi and that the rabbi
should look at it. So the rabbi takes the ring and he
looks at it and he looks on the inside inscribed on the
inside it says ממזר. Mamzer.
So this is how the grandmother was dealing with her guilt about
this situation, right? So leaving this like time bomb to go off.
Anyway, so so I so I said to the guy who told
me the story so what did the rabbi do? So he said
he did he did the only thing he could do. He fainted.
So which was a way of buying him time and then you
know they rushed him off or whatever and then he made a
phone call. So
anyway, the answer was like לאו כל כמינך, Lav Kol Keminach, that
has no halakhic weight, you just ignore it.
So
what was it you said? The the mother of the groom came
to him under like right before the חופה? Chuppah? Yeah. And said
it was like רב Rav I don't know, yeah רב סולובייצ'יק Rav
Soloveitchik maybe I don't know I don't know. And like she and
you said that he she said you know I have to tell
you that I'm in this child you know the חתן Chosson is
a ממזר. Mamzer. And he said, I don't believe you.
Right. So yeah that's basically it, you know, we dismiss the testimony.
Now there of course it would only be like negative. Here and
here too I mean she's already married to רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
There it's a little different like he hadn't yet started to live
with either man it seems like and the question was which man
was her husband but nevertheless we just dismiss the testimony.
Yeah. First thing why we don't say עד אחד נאמן באיסורין? Eid
Echad Ne'eman B'Issurin? Meaning like this woman this mother is saying
she's married to another guy! I understand, but אין דבר שבערוה פחות
משניים Ein Davar Shebe’erva Pachos Mishnayim means that things that have to
do with personal status are not assessed as normal איסורין, Issurin, okay?
And also again, it also has to do with sort of like
like
that's the basic answer.
But if there were two witnesses that said yeah, I was at
the store when he purchased it and I saw the I saw
the receipt and it was for a dollar fifty, then they would
be believed.
Yeah. And now we're going to get to that case. Okay. I
mean there's other points too, the main point is that דבר שבערוה,
Davar Shebe’erva,
but the other law points also observed like is that it's not
like it's just between me and whether this is an עבירה Aveira
or not an עבירה. Aveira. It it has implications for other people
and other people's sort of rights and so on and therefore it
also puts it into the more standard category of עדות. Eidus. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so we're not
done with this case. So we've dismissed שמואל, Shmuel, we've dismissed this
mother testifying. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב חסדא Amru Lei Rabbanan L'Rav Chisda
and now the rabbi said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, אמאי הא
איכא סהדי בעידית דידעי דההוא יומא הוה ביה שוה פרוטה, Amai Hei
Ika Sahadi Be'Idis Dyad'ei De'Hahu Yoma Hava Beh Shaveh Pruta, why are
you going to allow this woman and say that it was not
a good marriage? There are witnesses in over in עידית Idis some
place some foreign country מדי Madai that was there at the time
and the story is is that they are saying that it was
worth a פרוטה, Pruta, so it's like עד מפי עד, Eid Mipi
Eid, but at least we're telling you the con- we there is
evidence to be had that it was worth a פרוטה. Pruta. So
he says, you know what? השתא מיהא לא ליתנהו קמן, Hashata Miha
Lo Leisnu Kaman, I mean so what? They're not here now. You
snooze, you lose. Okay. לאו היינו דרבי חייא חנינא, Lav Hainu De'Rabbi
Chiya Chanina, I'll give you like the story with רבי חנינא, Rabbi
Chanina, דאמר רבי חנינא, De'Amar Rabbi Chanina, עידי בצד איסתן ותינשא, Eidei
B'Tzad Istin Ve'Tinaser,
so the witnesses are over, so this was a case about a
woman who was taken as the daughters of שמואל Shmuel actually who
were taken as captives and basically they said that they were not
forced to have sex and therefore they were allowed to marry other
men. But the הלכה halakhah is is that that's only because there
were not witnesses that saw them being taken captive. If there was
actually if there was direct evidence that they were taken captive they
wouldn't be believed to say that they had not they had not
been raped. So somebody said in that
case... So Abaye and Rava so that was his response. Now there's
a difference and Abaye and Rava לא סבירי ליה להא דרב חסדא.
lo savari leh l'ha deRav Chisda. They did not agree with Rav
Chisda's פסק psak that we should just dismiss those witnesses.
אי הקילו בשבויה דמנוולה נפשה גבי שבאי, im heikilu b'shvuyah deminavla nafsha
gabei shavai, just because we're lenient by a שבויה shvuyah and
now some have these take out the next three words which is
hard to explain what they're doing here, but let me just let
me take it out. If we're going to be lenient by a
שבויה shvuyah even if there are witnesses that a woman was taken
captive, we don't know that she was raped. So in that case
to dismiss the fact that there are witnesses that saw her taken
captive, but even that is not direct evidence that they're אסור, assur,
right? It just you know we're just going to presume and we
won't believe them to say otherwise, but that's only a rabbinic type
of a concern. So we could dismiss it if the witnesses aren't
here. But here we're saying that there are witnesses they know that
she's married to the first guy. How could we not be concerned
about that? Okay, so if there's knowledge that there are witnesses somewhere
else, we have to be concerned about it. Okay, that's now. תוספות
Tosafot by the way says right that it's too extreme that רב
חסדא Rav Chisda here would not be concerned about these witnesses. So
take a look at תוספות Tosafot he says ואיכא סהדי בעידי v'ika
sahdi b'idai or באורי, b'uri, he says אין לפרש שנחוש לשמא איכא
סהדי, ein l'faresh she'neichosh l'shema ika sahdi, the second one. דאם כן
אין לדבר סוף ולא למי איכא למיחש. d'im ken ein ladavar sof
v'lo l'mi i'ka l'meichash.
Clearly the case is not just hypothetically who knows maybe there are
witnesses. It sounds like there's something concrete, some knowledge that there are
witnesses. On the one hand ונמי ליכא לפרש דאיכא סהדי דידעי דבאותה
שעה הוה שוה פרוטה, v'nami leika l'faresh d'ika sahdi d'yadi d'v'o'u'sha'ta hava
shaveh prutah, you can't say that it's like people know
that there are witnesses that they heard witnesses say that it was
a שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah because in that case דפשיטא דעל זה
ראוי להחמיר d'pshita d'al zeh ra'uy l'hachmir there would be no way
רב חסדא Rav Chisda could be so lenient in that case. תוספות
Tosafot says logically we have to find a middle case here. Either
extreme doesn't make sense. אלא נראה לרי לפרש ואיכא סהדי כלומר יצא
קול שיש עדים באורי ella nir'ah l'RI l'faresh v'ika sahdi klomar yatza
kol she'yesh eydim b'uri או במדינת הים. o b'midinat hayam.
We don't know for sure. There's a rumor that there are witnesses
who know that it was a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot doesn't feels it's too hard to imagine that if there's
like people say I heard witnesses say that it was a שוה
פרוטה shaveh prutah that we could dismiss that. But if there's a
rumor then he says that's רב חסדא Rav Chisda is willing to
dismiss and אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava are not willing to dismiss. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Okay, that line by the
way that by a שבויה shvuyah דמנוולה נפשה גבי
שבאי deminavla nafsha gabei shavai she like makes herself degrading by the
captor, how is that relevant is not exactly clear. Could mean that
just because the captor maybe took advantage of her doesn't mean he
raped her or it could whatever, maybe it means that she'll make
herself that the captor won't want to have sex with her. Anyway
it's a hard line, but the basic point is we're lenient by
שבויה shvuyah which is דרבנן derabbanan that doesn't mean we're going to
be lenient by a case of אשת איש. eishet ish. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אשתייר מההיא משפחה בסורא, Ishtayir me'hi
mishpacha b'Sura,
there was some you know in Sura there were some descendants from
that family, from the family that רב חסדא Rav Chisda basically let
this woman marry the second guy and then they had kids and
grandkids and whatever and there were some descendants from that ופירשו רבנן
מיניה upirshu rabanan mineih and the rabbis, meaning the המון
עם hamon am where
their status was they followed the authority of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
it was considered that she was okay, the kids were okay, they
married in with the family and so on, but the rabbis were
a little bit more מחמיר machmir not to marry into the family
because yeah basically because of ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. So לא משום
דסבירא להו דשמואל, lav mishum d'svira lehu d'Shmuel,
not because they're concerned about שמואל Shmuel that even less than a
פרוטה prutah we have to be concerned that it's worth a פרוטה
prutah somewhere in מדינת הים medinat hayam אלא משום דסבירא להו כאביי
ורבא. ella mishum d'svira lehu k'Abaye v'Rava. No, but because that there
were witnesses that there was at least a rumor that there were
witnesses that knew for sure that it was a שוה פרוטה. shaveh
prutah. Okay, so the basic conclusion of the גמרא Gemara besides that
it's a little bit disturbing this idea of having these double standards,
right, which is issues that we have today too like you know
but okay that we're going to find even more of as we
do מסכת masechet you know קידושין Kiddushin about you know different types
of standards by יוחסין. yuchsin. But anyway the basic conclusion of the
גמרא Gemara is that if it's clear it's less than a פרוטה
prutah here we're not worried about what it might be worth elsewhere,
but if there's some question of is it worth a פרוטה prutah
here or certainly in cases where there's like a knowledge that there
are witnesses who might have that information or whatever, we cannot just
so easily dismiss that information. Let's just keep on going.
Okay ההוא גברא דאקדש בשטיסא דאסא, hahu gavra d'ikadesh b'shatisa d'asa, a
man married a woman with like a stick of myrtle בשוקא b'shuka
in the marketplace. שלח רב אחא בר הונא לקמיה דרב יוסף, shalach
Rav Acha bar Huna l'kamei d'Rav Yosef, what's the story with this
case?
Is it worth a פרוטה? prutah?
Yeah.
שלח ליה נגדיה כרב ואיצטריך גט כשמואל. shalach leh nagdi k'Rav v'itztrich
get k'Shmuel. Clearly it's not worth a פרוטה. perutah. He picks up
a stick off the ground. Clearly it's not worth a פרוטה, perutah,
but we פוסק pasken like שמואל, Shmuel, he's concerned with שמואל. Shmuel.
Maybe it's worth a פרוטה perutah in מדי. Madai. So you need
to have a גט מספק get misafeik like שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel
is like, he has so much צרות, tzoros, every single case needs
a גט מספק. get misafeik. So number one, like שמואל, Shmuel, we
have to give a גט מספק, get misafeik, maybe it's worth a
פרוטה perutah in מדי. Madai. But by the way, another הלכה halacha
here is we have to give him lashes. Why do we have
to give him lashes? דרב מנגיד, deRav mangid, רב Rav gave lashes
אדם מקדש בשוקא, adam mekadesh bashuka, somebody who marries a woman in
the marketplace. This is very important, you know, because this is basically
saying marriage is a serious institution. You don't get into it without
like, you know, significant planning and foresight. And so even though halachically
a marriage is binding if it's done on the, you know, instantaneous,
like spontaneously. You
know,
you gave it, there was witnesses, she accepted it or whatever. Nevertheless,
there was a,
רב Rav wanted to prevent that, like you need to go through
a process of foresight and treating it seriously. You don't do it
סתם stam in the marketplace. ומן דמקדש בביאה, u'man de'mekadesh beviah, somebody
who does קידושין kiddushin with sex. We'll talk about that like later,
maybe tomorrow. ועל דמקדש בלא שידוכי, v'al de'mekadesh belo shiduchei, or somebody
who does קידושין kiddushin without any engagement period, for the same reason.
That's very similar to the issue about in the marketplace. Now, the
issue about מקדש בביאה mekadesh beviah might be similar, because that basically
is sending a message. Like the whole idea of two stages of
קידושין kiddushin and נישואין nisuin is saying that this is not just
all about the, you know, about like having sex. You know, this
is like a, there's like a commitment and that you're entering into
that that has more, is much more than just the sexual life
and it's sort of is something that that endures. You know, it's
a contract, it's binding. So it comes even the קידושין kiddushin becomes
a reality before the sex becomes the reality. Right? So and you
know, marriages have trouble, have, you know, there're times that they have
trouble. And that even when sometimes the, you know, there's some physical,
like they're not as intimate and they're not as close or whatever,
it doesn't mean the marriage all of a sudden disappears instantaneously. Like
you gotta, you try to work through the hard times. You know,
so a lot of that is created through this sense that you
start with קידושין kiddushin and then you move on to ביאה. beiah.
You don't start with ביאה. beiah. That makes it all like about
that, that makes
it like something, you know, that doesn't have that sense of like
commitment that's independent of that. So that's part of the problem of
קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah.
Technically it's binding, but it's, you know, it sends the wrong message
about what this whole, what, what marriage is about. What? בלא שידוכי?
belo shiduchei? Without, without engagement, without a process of engagement. Meaning like
those cases where he wants to marry a wife for a day,
we had that in other.
Yeah, or the cases we had earlier in the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah,
there are cases like that in the גמרא. Gemara.
It was רב Rav who, Rabbi who did the temporary marriage.
Okay, so that's a good question. We are, I don't know. We
also had cases in the גמרא, Gemara, remember that a woman said,
"Give me to drink," and the guy says, "I'll give you some
wine, you'll marry me with this wine," she says, "Just give me
to drink." So that would, I mean, there're, but that's, but those
are all good reasons why you don't want to be doing it
בשוק bashuk and בלא שידוכי. belo shiduchei. You know, so you want
it to be treated seriously. Okay. ועל, ve'al, in addition, let's just
go a little bit more to finish this. דמבטל גיטא, de'mevatel gita,
somebody who's מבטל mevatel a גט. get. Right, which had to do
with that whole case in גיטין. Gittin. Now רש"י Rashi says it's
even if you told the שליח, shaliach, we're just afraid that the
שליח shaliach won't listen to you or whatever. תוספות Tosafot says no,
no, no, it's when you were מבטל mevatel it not in the
presence of the שליח. shaliach. So that's a case where, you know,
the woman could get in serious trouble if that happens. So he
was going to give lashes if you did that. ועל דמסר מודעא
אגיטא, v'al de'masar moda'a agita, somebody who's being compelled by בית דין
beis din to give a גט, get, but he still wants to
subvert בית דין. beis din. So he, before he gives the גט,
get, gives testimony to witnesses that he's not giving it of his
own free will. So clearly he's trying, it's gonna be creating a
lot of trouble there. ועל דמצער שלוחא דרבנן, v'al de'metza'ar shilucha derabbanan,
or the בית דין beis din sent somebody, a court officer, to
go call him to court, and what he does is he beats
up the court officer. He physically or verbally abuses him, which is
a way of rejecting rabbinic authority. Okay. ועל דחלה שמתא עילוי תלתין
יומין, v'al de'chala shamta iluay telasin yomin, or somebody who allowed a
נידוי niduy to rest on him for thirty days. Right, because the
whole idea is that that, that shows a disregard. The נידוי niduy
was a form of rabbinic censure. And if you don't feel you
have to do anything about it to try to, you know, reconcile,
to try to, whatever, you're just dismissive of it, we gotta take
things to the next level. Okay, and we gotta give you physical
lashes.
וחתנא דדייר בבי חמוה. ve'achasna de'dayer be'bei chamuay. Okay, and a son-in-law
that lives in his mother-in-law's house. Because then there'll be, maybe, suspect,
there'll be questions about is he actually sleeping with his mother-in-law. דדייר
אין. de'dayer in. Now the question is does it mean mother-in-law
that there's no father-in-law, the father is dead or divorced or whatever?
You know, it's not exactly clear. דדייר אין חליף לא. de'dayer in,
chalif lo. Only if he's living there, not if he's just passing
by, not if he just visits on a regular basis. So the
גמרא Gemara says, is that true? דההוא חתנא דחליף אבבא דבי חמוה.
de'hahu chasna de'chalif ababa de'bei chamuay. There was a son-in-law that regularly
visited by his, the door of his mother-in-law, ונגדיה רב ששת, ve'nagdei
Rav Sheshet, and רב ששת Rav Sheshet gave him lashes. So you
see even just visiting on a regular basis is a problem? No,
the גמרא *Gemara* says ההוא מידעם הוה דיימא חמשה מיניה *hahu midam
havei daima chamsei minei*. No, no, no, there there was concrete suspicions.
That wasn't just a סתם *stam* case.
People were rumoring that
he was having an affair with his mother-in-law. Hey, like you say,
I don't want to go to your mother's. Right. נהרדאי אמרי *Nahardai
amrei*, נהרדאי *Nahardai* says let's just finish this point, נהרדאי אמרי *Nahardai
amrei*, בכולו לא מנגיד רב *bekulu lo menaged Rav*, רב *Rav* would
not give lashes on any of those cases, אלא על דמקדש בביאה
בלא שידוכי *ela al demekadesh bevia belo shiduchei*, only two things combined,
קידושין *Kiddushin* with sex and without שידוכין *shiduchin* beforehand. You know, it's
like right on
the spot you're so eager to have sex that you just, you
know, you know, it came with nothing beforehand and it's all about
the sex. It's not about a serious entering into an institution of
marriage. ואיכא דאמרי *ve'ika de'amrei*, ואפילו בשידוכי נמי *ve'afillu beshiduchei nami*, even
קידושי ביאה *kidushei via* with like an engagement period would be inappropriate,
משום פריצותא *mishum pritzuta*, because that would just be considered to be
like, you know, too, like פריצות *pritzus* is the opposite of צניעות
*tznius*, you know, too immodest, you know, too immoral to sort of
make it, you know, to just make it all about sex. I
want to just read very quickly two very, one line from תוספות
*Tosafot* or two lines from two תוספות *Tosafot*. תוספות *Tosafot* first of
all says about בכולו לא מנגיד רב
*bekulu lo menaged Rav*. You see that? So it says על זה
סומכים החתנים בזמן הזה שדרין בבית חמותם *al zeh somchim hachasanim bazman
hazeh shedarin bevei chamosam*. That's why nowadays sons-in-law live in their mother-in-law's
house. ואפילו למאן דחייש לעיל *ve'afillu leman dechaish le'eil*, even the one
that says that we, you know, because that's the conclusion that רב
*Rav* did not give lashes. But even according to the position that
רב *Rav* gave lashes, מה שדרין עכשיו בבית חמותם היינו בשביל טובת
הנאה שדרין בלא שכירות בבית *mah shedarin achshav bevei chamosam hainu bishvil
tovas hana'ah shedarin belo sechiros babayis*. No, no, no, nowadays they do
it just to save rent. So therefore דאיכא הוכחה שאינם דרים בשביל
חמותם *de'ika hochacha she'einam darin bishvil chamosam*. It's clear they're not doing
it because they're having an affair. אלא בשביל שאר טובות שעושים להם
*ela bishvil shear tovos she'osim lahem*. You know, they're doing it because
they get free rent. Okay. And the last one is משום פריצותא
*mishum pritzuta* about קידושי ביאה *kidushei via*. I just want to read
מפרש רבינו תם היינו פריצותא לפי שצריך או עדי ביאה או עדי
יחוד *mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam hainu pritzuta lefi shetzarich o edei via o
edei yichud*. So רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says the פריצותא *pritzuta* was
that you need witnesses for the ביאה *via* and that was פריצותא
*pritzuta*. But תוספות *Tosafot* doesn't like that and if you skip to
the last line of תוספות *Tosafot* he says אלא נראה לרי דהיינו
פריצותא שעושים תחלת קניינם בביאה דומיא דמקדש בשידוכי *ela nira le'Ri de'hainu
pritzuta she'osim techilas kinyanam bevia dumya demekadesh bishiduchei*. It's like that you
started it all off with being about sex, you know, and that's
really the פריצותא *pritzuta* problem. קידושין *Kiddushin* is about entering into the
seriousness of the, you know, institution, of the commitment and, you know,
and it's not all reduced to sex and it's not something that
you just do at a spur of the moment, you know, and
that's sort of what רב *Rav* was coming to try to control.
Okay.